Preliminary Guide to the American Economic Association Records, 1886-2008 and undated RL.00033
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Economic Association records
1886-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Economic Association
RL.00033
420.5 Linear Feet
346,763 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Permission from AEA is required to access materials less than 50 years old. Contact Research Services for assistance.
Provenance
The American Economic Association Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001-2009.
Biographical Note
Primary professional association for economists in the United States, organized in 1885. It publishes the American Economic Review, the Journal of Economic Literature, and the Journal of Economic Perspectives.
Collection Overview
Primarily records of the American Economic Review, (Accession 2001-0118) specifically journal office files consisting of correspondence, manuscript, book review, and referee files (1969-1998). There are also records for the organization (1886-1984) and for its Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP 1972-1993), including histories, reports, minutes, statistics, as well as membership, account, conference, board member, miscellaneous, and newsletter or editorial office files. Some CSWEP material is also present as 371 machine-readable records. There is a small set of journal office records for the Journal of Economic Literature (1975, 1984-1994 and undated). In addition, there are 50 black-and-white photographs of former association presidents, a 39"x10" black-and-white group photograph taken at an unidentified meeting, 48 rolls of microfilm from the various journals (mostly AER), 63 microfiche of Journal of Economic Literature correspondence ([1968]-1980), and 7 reel-to-reel audiotapes.
Addition (2001-0082) (4000 items, 9.6 linear feet; dated 1998-1999) includes records for the American Economic Review, including correspondence and referee files for rejected and withdrawn articles (1998), accepted articles (1999), and papers and proceedings (1999).
Addition (2002-0215) (21000 items, 33.4 linear feet; dated 1999-2001) contains records for the American Economic Review, including editorial correspondence, referee reports, and manuscripts for rejected articles (1999-2000) and accepted articles (March-December 2001) and papers and proceedings (2000-2001). Also includes 37 electronic documents on one floppy disk.
The collection consists of 15 additional accessions dating from 2003 to 2008 with over 200 additional boxes. These additions have not been processed, but are available for research with permission from the American Economic Association. Please consult the Preliminary Description of Unprocessed Collection (below) for details.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted: Original audiovisual materials require reformatting prior to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
Women economists; Machine-readable records; Economics -- Book reviews -- Periodicals; Economics -- Congresses; Economics -- Societies, etc.; Economics -- Research; Black-and-white photographs; Economics -- Periodicals; Microfiche; Microfilms; Audiotapes; American Economic Association. Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession; American Economic Association
- Accession (2001-0118)
  Scope and Contents note
  Records of the American Economic Review (225,000 items, dated 1886-1998), specifically journal office files with correspondence, manuscript, book review, and referee files (1969-1998). Also records for the organization (1886-1984) and for its Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP 1972-1993), including histories, reports, minutes, statistics, as well as membership, account, conference, board member, misc., and newsletter or editorial office files. Some CSWEP material is also present as 371 machine-readable records. There is a small set of journal office records for the Journal of Economic Literature (JEL 1975, 1984-1994 and n.d.) In addition, there are 50 black-and-white photographs of former association presidents, a 39"x10" black-and-white group photograph taken at an unidentified meeting, 48 rolls of microfilm from the various journals, 63 microfiche of JEL correspondence ([1968]-1980), and 7 reel-to-reel audiotapes.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Written permission from AEA required for access to materials less than fifty years old.
  - Minutes of Council and Executive Council, AEA, 1888-1908, and Annual Meetings, 1886-1924
    - AEA. Histories, A.W. Coats, 1952-1963; Journal of Economic Literature, Mark Perlman, editor. Correspondence, [1968] 1970-1980; Organization, [1885]; Minutes, 1886-1904; Membership, 1890-1896 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1902-1906; Membership, 1890-1896; Accounts, 1889-1894; Annual Meetings, 1886-1905 (Box 2)
    - Annual Meetings, 1908-1924 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of Secretary-Treasurer, AEA, including Reports, 1888-1964
    - Correspondence. Incoming, 1888 March- 1896 Febuary (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1893 October-1894 December (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1894-1898 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1898-1899 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, Incoming, 1896-1900 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1900-1902 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1903-1908 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1909; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1911; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, including Reports, 1912-1913; Thomas N. Carver, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1914-1915; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1916-1917; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919; Allyn A. Young, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1922-1923; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1924; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 19)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1925; Ray B. Westerfield, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1926; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1927; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1928; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1929-1931; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1932-1933 (A-Z); Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1933-1935; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 26-27)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1936; Frederick S. Deibler and James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurers (Box 28)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1937-1938; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 29)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1939-1940; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 30)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1940-1941; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 31)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1942; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 32)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1943; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 33)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1944-1945; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 34)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1945-1946; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1947-1948; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 36)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1949-1950; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 37)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1951; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 38)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1952; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 39)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1953; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 40)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1954; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 41)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1955-1956; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 42)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1956-1957; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 43)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1957; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 44)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1957-1958; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 45)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1958; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 46)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1959; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 47-48)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1960; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 49-50)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1961; James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 51-52)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1962; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 53-54)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1963; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 55-56)
    - Correspondence, including reports, 1964; Harold F. Williamson, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 57)
  - Correspondence of Secretary-Treasurer with AEA Committees, Miscellaneous Business, 1930-1961
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1930-1939; Frederick S. Deibler, Secretary-Treasurer 1930-1935 and James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer 1936-1939 (Box 58)
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1940-1945 (1959); James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 59)
    - Correspondence: Committees, AEA, and Miscellaneous Business, 1946-1950 (1956); James Washington Bell, Secretary-Treasurer (Box 60-61)
  - American Economic Review: Correspondence of Managing Editor, Davis R. Dewey, with editors, contributors, etc.., 1910-1940
    - Correspondence of AEA re founding journal and special editorial correspondence, AER, 1910-1940 (Box 62)
    - AER statistics, 1911-1923; Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1911-1917 (Box 63)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1910-1917 (Box 64-69)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1918-1919 (Box 70-71)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1920 (Box 72)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1921 (Box 73)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1922 (Box 74)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1923 (Box 75)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1924-1925 (Box 76)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1925-1926 (Box 77)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1927-1928 (Box 78)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1928 (Box 79)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1929 (Box 80)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1930 (Box 81)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1931 (Box 82)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1932 (Box 83)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1933 (Box 84)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1934 (Box 85)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1935 (Box 86)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1936 (Box 87)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1937 (Box 88)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1938 (Box 89)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1939 (Box 90)
    - Correspondence of Davis R. Dewey with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1940 (Box 91)
  - American Economic Review: Correspondence of Managing Editor, Paul T. Homan, 1941-1951, with editors, contributors, etc.
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1941 (Box 92)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1942-1943 (Box 93)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan, Managing Editor, 1941-1951, and Fritz Machlup, Acting Managing Editor, 1944 July-1945 August, with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1944-1945 (Box 94)
    - Correspondence of Paul T. Homan, Managing Editor, 1941-1951, and Fritz Machlup, Acting Managing Editor, 1944 July-1945 August, with editors and authors of articles and communications, 1945-1949 (Box 95)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, book reviews, articles, and other internal documents
    - AEA internal papers, ca. 1958-1968 (Box 96-104)
    - Foreign correspondence, 1952-1959, 1968 (Box 105-106)
    - Exchanges-Internal memoranda, 1953-1956 (Box 107)
    - Internal memoranda, 1954-1964 (Box 108)
    - Survey articles, 1957-1963 (Box 109)
    - Survey articles; budget; book reviews, 1952-1960, 1963 (Box 110)
    - Book reviews, 1963-1966 (Box 111)
    - Book reviews; general correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 112)
    - General correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 113-118)
    - General correspondence; articles and correspondence, 1968 (Box 119)
    - Articles and correspondence, 1968 (Box 120-121)
    - Miscellany, 1962-1973, 1980-1982 (Box 122-128)
    - Accounts received for back issues, 1961, 2 bound volumes (Box 129)
    - General correspondence, 1968-1979 (Box 130-131)
    - Office correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 132-134)
    - Miscellaneous, 1980-1982 (Box 135)
  - C. P. Kindleberger Papers
    - AEA Papers, C. P. Kindleberger, 1984 (Box 136-144)
    - C. P. Kindleberger; AER rejects, prior to 1969 July (Box 145)
  - AER acceptances, rejects, withdrawn, and papers and proceedings
    - AER rejects, prior to 1969 July; 1969-1980 (Box 146-376)
    - AER rejects, comments, and correspondence, 1968-1983 (Box 377-396)
    - AER acceptances and refereed remarks, 1969-1979 (Box 397-432)
    - AER acceptance and rejection cards, 1969-1981 (Box 433-444)
    - AER "No author card" and miscellaneous rejects, 1981-1985 (Box 445)
    - AER rejects, 1981 (Box 446-449)
    - AER rejects, 1982-1983 (Box 450-453)
    - AER published, 1983 (Box 454-457)
    - AER published, 1984 (Box 458-462)
    - AER published, 1985 (Box 463-467)
    - AER rejects, 1983-1985 (Box 468-517)
    - AER rejects, 1985 (Box 518-544)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1986 (Box 545)
    - AER published, 1986 (Box 546-550)
    - AER rejects, 1986 (Box 551-590)
    - AER published, 1987 (Box 591-594)
    - AER rejects, 1987 (Box 595-629)
    - AER published, 1988 (Box 630-633)
    - AER rejects, 1988 (Box 634-664)
    - AER rejects, 1988 (Box 665-669)
    - AEA rejects, 1989 (Box 670-694)
    - AER published 1989 (Box 695-698)
    - AER rejects, 1989 (Box 699-714)
    - AER published, 1990 (Box 715-719)
    - AER miscellaneous, 1987-1988 (Box 720)
    - AER rejects, 1990 (Box 721-748)
    - AER rejects and withdrawn; AER acceptances, 1991 (Box 749-750)
    - AER acceptances, 1991 (Box 751-756)
    - AER rejects, 1991 (Box 757-760)
    - AER rejects, comments and correspondence to, 1991 (Box 761-769)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1992 (Box 770-771)
    - AER acceptances, 1992 (Box 772-778)
    - AER rejects, 1992 (Box 779-790)
    - AER acceptances, 1993 (Box 791-801)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1993 (Box 802)
    - AER rejects, 1993 (Box 803-810)
    - AER acceptances, 1994 (Box 811-818)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1994 (Box 819)
    - AER rejects, 1994 (Box 820-826)
    - AER acceptances, 1995 (Box 827-831)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1995 (Box 832)
    - AER rejects, 1995 (Box 833-839)
    - AER acceptances, 1996 (Box 840-849)
    - AER papers and proceedings, 1996 (Box 850)
    - AER rejects, 1996 (Box 851-858)
    - AER acceptances, rejections, and withdrawals, 1997 (Box 859-874)
    - AER acceptances, 1998 (Box 875-888)
  - JEL correspondence, acceptance, and other files
    - JEL correspondence, 1979-[1991?] (Box 889-906)
    - JEL [acceptances?], 1990-1994 (Box 907-915)
    - JEL inactive, 1989-1990 (Box 916-918)
    - JEL office, 1988-1994 (Box 919)
  - Secretary-Treasurer Files, 1949-1980s; 1
    - Association of American Law Schools, 1967-1969 (Box 920)
    - FInance Committee, 1969-1975; 3 folders (Box 920)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes memos and documents related to committee business
    - Committee on Hiring Practices, 1974 (Box 920)
      Includes documents related to Job Openings for Economists
    - Journal of Economic Literature, 1970-1974 (Box 920)
    - Nominating Committee, 1955-1975; 4 folders (Box 920)
      Includes documents for routine committee business
    - Executive Committee, 1967-1974 (Box 920)
    - Committee for Oversight of Operations and Publishing, 1972 (Box 921)
    - Executive Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 921)
    - Visiting Scientists Program, 1966-1972 (Box 921)
    - Counsel, 1944-1961 (Box 921)
    - Economics Institute, 1968-1979; 4 folders (Box 921)
    - Behavioral Sciences Planning Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 921)
    - Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1970 (Box 921)
      Includes files related to publishing Association journals
    - Economic Education, 1965-1970 (Box 921)
    - Economic Labor Market, 1961-1970 (Box 921)
    - International Economic Association, 1964-1974 (Box 922)
    - Committee on Research and Publications, 1964-1975; 2 folders (Box 922)
    - NSF Revision of Spec. List, 1967-1968 (Box 922)
      Includes documents related to publication classification systems
    - Tolles, Arnold (Correspondence and Advisory Committee), 1965-1968 (Box 922)
      Includes documents related to committee work on organizaton of economics profession
    - ASSA Officers, 1979 (Box 922)
    - Academic Labor Market, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 922)
    - Amnesty International, 1983 (Box 923)
    - Army Science Board, 1979-1980 (Box 923)
    - Arthur Andersen Co., 1970-1979; 3 folders (Box 923)
      Includes documents related to Association finances
    - Behavioral and Social Sciences, 1971 (Box 923)
      Includes documents related to professional organizations in other fields
    - Black Caucus, 1970-1974 (Box 923)
      Includes documents related to promoting opportunities for minority economists
    - Cato Institute, 1980-1981 (Box 923)
    - Executive Committee Chair's Group, 1970-1984 (Box 923)
    - Change Magazine, 1976 (Box 924)
    - Executive Committee, 1982 (Box 924)
    - Commission on the Humanities, 1964-1979 (Box 924)
    - Commission on Non-traditional Study, 1972-1973 (Box 924)
      Includes documents related to new forms of post-secondary education
    - Investment Income, 1971-1979 (Box 924)
    - National Science Foundation Instructions and Materials, 1964 (Box 924)
    - National Science Foundation Crank File, 1970 (Box 924)
      Includes documents for various unfulfilled reviewer requests
    - Handbook - Agreements, Correspondence, etc, 1964-1969; 2 folders (Box 924)
      Includes files for Association handbook
    - Marquis WHO'S Who, 1971-1973 (Box 925)
      Includes documents for directory of economists
    - Yale (Rich Ruggles), 1971 (Box 925)
      Includes documents related to computerization and the Association
    - Handbook Applications (Non-Members), 1969 (Box 925)
    - Handbook Material, 1964 (Box 925)
    - Econometric Society, 1969-1970 (Box 925)
      Includes files related to Association handbook and Econometric Society involvement
    - Foreign Student Screening Project (FSSP), 1965-1969; 3 folders (Box 925)
      Includes files related to grant agreement with the US Department of State
    - Ledger, 1965 (Box 926)
      Includes uncategorized ledger
    - Members Typed, 1974; 2 folders (Box 926)
      Includes letters related to questionnaire responses for member directory
    - Handbook Preparation, 1969 (Box 926)
    - Guide Contributions, 1965 (Box 926)
    - Foreign Student Screening Project (FSSP), 1964-1965 (Box 926)
    - Old Photographs, 1958-1965 and undated (Box 926)
      Includes photographs of past prominent members of the Association
    - Photographs for 100th Anniversary of the AEA, 1986 (Box 926)
      Includes photograph of Verein fur Socialpolitik members at 1928 meeting sent to the AEA as an anniversary present. Photograph includes Gerhard Colm, Friedrich Hayek, Fritz Machlup, Ludwig Mises, and Hans Neisser, among others
    - French Statistical Society Medal, undated (Box 926)
      Includes bronze medallion commemorating membership in the society
    - Newspaper Articles, 1954-1969 (Box 926)
      Includes various newspaper clippings about economists
    - Committee on Research and Publications, 1964-1967 (Box 926)
    - Foreign Student Screening Project (FSSP), 1965-1970; 5 folders (Box 926)
    - Foreign Student Screening Project (FSSP), 1967 (Box 927)
    - Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP), 1980-1985; 10 folders (Box 927)
      Includes documents for CSWEP activities at annual conference, budgets, meetings, membership, liaison to the Econometric Society, and surveys of women in economics
    - Newsletter Master Copies, 1974-1986 (Box 927)
    - Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP), 1978-1984; 14 folders (Box 928)
      Includes documents for CSWEP activities at annual conference, rosters, newsletters, and correspondence
    - Committee on the Status of Women in the Economics Profession (CSWEP), 1979-1984; 13 folders (Box 929)
      Includes documents for CSWEP activities at annual conference, correspondence, and other meetings
    - Budget Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 930)
    - American Economic Review, 1970-1977; 2 folders (Box 930)
    - Lifetime Member Contributions, 1976-1980 (Box 930)
    - Papers and Proceedings, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 930)
      Includes documents related to Papers and Proceedings issues of American Economic Review
    - Executive Committee, 1973-1981 (Box 930)
    - Kingsport Press, 1983-1984 (Box 930)
      Includes orders for issues of Journal of Economic Literature
    - American Economic Review: Clower, 1980-1984; 2 folders (Box 930)
      Includes correspondence about journal budget
    - American Economic Review: Ashenfelter, 1984 (Box 930)
      Includes correspondence about editorial board membership
    - Executive Committee, 1973-1983; 4 folders (Box 930)
    - Executive Committee, 1979-1984 and undated; 9 folders (Box 931)
    - Executive Committee, 1974-1985; 5 folders (Box 932)
    - Committee on Economic Education, 1983-1984 (Box 932)
    - Committee on Economic Education, 1978-1982 (Box 932A)
    - Committee on Editorships, 1976 (Box 932A)
    - Census Advisory Committee, 1970-1984; 3 folders (Box 932A)
    - Committee on Computerization, 1975-1975 (Box 933)
    - Carter Committee, 1976 (Box 933)